Inventory of the Eleanor Bisbee Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Eleanor Bisbee Papers
1891-1956
56018
Bisbee, Eleanor.
18 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 8 envelopes (8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives. Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection relates to the history of the government of Turkey in the twentieth century, U.S.-Turkish relations, and Eleanor Bisbee's book The New Turks: Pioneers of the Republic, 1920-1950 (University of Pennsylvania Press, 1951). It consists of correspondence, drafts of writings, speeches, memoranda, notes, pamphlets, press summaries, clippings, maps, and photographs and includes original writings by Eleanor Bisbee as well as translations of writings by Resat Güntekin, Abdülhak Şinasi Hisar, Yakup Karaosmanoğlu, Ahmet Emin Yalman, the Milli Partisi, and an interview with Kemal Atatürk, 1922.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1956.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Separated Materials
Photographs have been separated to the Photograph Collection.
Related Materials
Hidayet Dagdeviren collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Christina Phelps Harris papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Tarik Zafer Tunaya typescript, Hoover Institution Archives
Ahmet Emin Yalman papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
July 22, 1893 Born, Beverly, New Jersey
1915 AB, Tufts College
1929 PhD in philosophy, University of Cincinnati
1930-1931 Assistant professor of philosophy and civilization; acting head of department of philosophy, University of Cincinnati
1931-circa 1942 Professor of philosophy at Robert College and the American College for Girls, Istanbul
1942 Returned to the United States
1946 Author, The People of Turkey (East and West Association)
1951 Author, The New Turks: Pioneers of the Republic, 1920-1950 (University of Pennsylvania Press)
1952 Research associate for Turkish collections at the Hoover Institution
April 18, 1956 Died, Palo Alto, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection relates to the history of the government of Turkey in the twentieth century, U.S.-Turkish relations, and Eleanor Bisbee's book The New Turks: Pioneers of the Republic, 1920-1950 (University of Pennsylvania Press, 1951). It consists of correspondence, drafts of writings, speeches, memoranda, notes, pamphlets, press summaries, clippings, maps, and photographs; and includes original writings by Eleanor Bisbee as well as translations of writings by Resat Güntekin, Abdülhak Şinasi Hisar, Yakup Karaosmanoglu, Ahmet Emin Yalman, the Milli Partisi, and an interview with Kemal Atatürk, 1922.
The Correspondence is arranged in four groups according to original order. Although there is some overlap between the alphabetical correspondence and the correspondence regarding Turkish materials at the Hoover Institution, the latter focuses almost exclusively on Bisbee's work as a research associate and her knowledge of Turkish library materials.
The research materials in The New Turks: Pioneers of the Republic, 1920-1950 file consist largely of clippings and printed matter on Turkish history, politics, geography, economy, and foreign relations. Especially interesting is the coverage of Turkey's 1950 elections, with more information on this topic in the Press summaries series.
Almost all of the drafts that are included in the papers are carbon copies of typescripts and include holographic notes and edits. Additionally, the researcher should be aware that not all drafts are complete.
Similarly, many of the drafts of Yalman's Turkey in My Time in the Translations and edited works series are incomplete working drafts. Some bear the title "I Have a Story to Tell," which was changed to "Turkey in My Time" for publication. Translations of other notable Turkish works are included in this series.
Due in part to Bisbee's close collaboration with a number of individuals in regards to her writings and research on Turkish affairs, her papers include notes and writings by others, namely Kerim K. Key and Christina P. Harris. Only complete works were included in the Speeches and writings by others series; the remaining notes and writings remain in context throughout the collection.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Turkey--History--1918-1960.; Turkey--Politics and government--1918-1960.; Atatürk, Kemal, 1881-1938.; Güntekin, Resat Nuri, 1889-1956.; Hisar, Abdülhak Sinasi, 1888-1963.; Karaosmanoglu, Yakup Kadri, 1889-1974.; Yalman, Ahmet Emin, 1889-.
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1925-1956; 1 (Box 1)
  Contains article, certificate, diary and diary letters, and interview
  Arranged in alphabetical order by form
  - Article from Miami Herald about Bisbee's work as editor and director, 1925 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Certificate of membership from Near East Foundation, 1950 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Diary and diary letters from the Near East, 1936-1942 (Folder 1: 3-4)
  - Interview with Bisbee regarding Turkish collection at Hoover Library, 1956 February (Folder 1: 5)
- Correspondence, 1942-1958; 1-2 (Box 1-2)
  Consists of letters and enclosures, arranged in four groups (Personal, Alphabetical, Correspondence regarding Turkish materials at the Hoover Institution, and Ford Foundation Board of Overseas Research Project correspondence), then alphabetically or chronologically respectively
  - Personal, 1945-1955 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Alphabetical, 1942-1956 (Folder 1-2)
    - General, 1947-1954 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Aktan, Resat, 1947 (Folder 1: 8)
    - American Board Mission (Albert Dewey), 1947-1953 (Folder 1: 9)
    - American Council of Learned Societies (Mortimer Graves, George N. Kates, Charles Oddegard), 1949-1953 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Army Language School, Presidio of Monterey, 1952-1953 (Folder 1: 11)
    - Baba, Nüzhet (Turkish Embassy, Office of the Press Attaché), 1945-1946 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Barker, A. Zeki, 1953 (Folder 1: 13)
    - Basoğlu, Muzafer Sherif, 1945 (Folder 1: 14)
    - Benlioğlu, Nuri, 1950 (Folder 1: 15)
    - Birge, J. Kingsley, 1952 (Folder 1: 16)
    - Brodeur, Harold H., 1952 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Burns, Eleanor, 1947 (Folder 1: 18)
    - Çambel, Ali Bulent, 1948 and undated (Folder 1: 19)
    - Çambel, Hasan Cemil, 1948 (Folder 1: 20)
    - Çambel, Marion Amelia, 1956 (Folder 1: 21)
    - Cebesoy, Ali Fuat, 1953-1955 (Folder 1: 22)
    - The Chronicle (Paul C. Smith), 1947 (Folder 1: 23)
    - Dewey, Dora, 1949-1950 (Folder 1: 24)
    - Dwight, Adelaide, 1950-1952 (Folder 1: 25)
    - Esmer, Ahmet Sukru, 1948 (Folder 1: 26)
    - Gankin, Olga, 1953 (Folder 1: 27)
    - Germen, Aydin, 1948 (Folder 1: 28)
    - Hisar, Abdülhak Şinasi, 1954 (Folder 1: 29)
    - Howard, Harry N., 1948 (Folder 1: 30)
      All replies written by Kerim K. Key on behalf of Harry N. Howard
    - Hüseiyn, 1951-1952 (Folder 1: 31)
    - İğdemir, Uluğ, 1948 (Folder 1: 32)
    - Ina, 1952 (Folder 1: 33)
    - İsmen, İsmail, 1948-1955 (Folder 1: 34)
    - Key, Kerim K., 1950-1956 (Folder 1: 35)
    - Marshall, John, 1955 (Folder 1: 36)
    - McKillop, Marjorie, 1949-1955 (Folder 1: 37)
    - The New York Times (Orville Prescott), 1950 (Folder 1: 38)
    - Parsons, Edith, 1947 (Folder 1: 39)
    - Pektas, Mihri, 1946 (Folder 1: 40)
    - Saturday Evening Post (editor), 1948 (Folder 2: 1)
    - Scott, Harold L., 1951 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Sirmen, Sedad, 1947-1949 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Wright, Walter Livingston, Jr., 1948-1949 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Correspondence regarding Turkish materials at the Hoover Institution, 1953-1958 (Folder 2)
    - Undated. Correspondents include Şerif Mardin and Ithiel de Sola Pool (Folder 2: 5)
    - 1951 (Folder 2: 6)
    - 1952. Correspondents include Easton Rothwell and Enver Ziya Karal (Folder 2: 7)
    - 1953. Correspondents include Yavuz Abadan, Tahsin Bekir Balta, Leyla Cambel, Ali Fuat Cebesoy, Tanju Ergil, Olga Gankin, Emin Hekimgil, Ernest R. Hilgard, İsmail İsmen, Kerim K. Key, Mehmet Fuad Köprülü, Adnan Otuken, Sami N. Özerdim, Harold Scott, Tarik Z. Tunaya, Faik Resit Unak, World Affairs Council, and Ahmet Emin Yalman (Folder 2: 8-9)
    - 1954. Correspondents include Ali Fuat Cebesoy, Celaleddin Ezine,İsmail İsmen, John Marshall, Siddik Sami Onar, Sami N. Özerdim, and Ahmet Emin Yalman (Folder 2: 10)
    - 1955. Correspondents include Tevfik Biyikoglu, Kerim K. Key, Marjorie McKillop, and Ithiel de Sola Pool (Folder 2: 11)
    - 1956. Correspondents include Tevfik Biyikoglu, Cecil Brown, Olga Gankin, Kerim K. Key, and Tarik Z. Tunaya (Folder 2: 12)
  - Ford Foundation Board of Overseas Research Project correspondence, 1953-1954 (Folder 2: 13)
- Speeches and writings, 1919-1956; 2-4 (Box 2-4:)
  Contains drafts and printed copies of articles, reviews, essays, and pamphlets
  Arranged chronologically
  - "The Muddle East,", undated (Folder 2: 14)
  - Script ideas for Voice of America broadcast to Turkey, undated (Folder 2: 15)
  - "Our Partners, the Turks,", undated (Folder 2: 16)
  - "The Women of Turkey,", undated (Folder 2: 17)
  - Note cards from speech to Turkish Friendship Club, Stanford, 1919 May 19 (Folder 2: 18)
  - "Childhood's Double Standards,", 1920 December (Folder 2: 19)
  - Articles written about Deering Estate published in Miami Daily Metropolis News, 1922-1923 (Folder 2: 20-22)
  - "A Dairy Empire in the South," The Dairy Farmer, 1924 February 1 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Opinion articles published in The Nash Journal, 1927 January-October (Folder 2: 24)
  - "Hints from the Advertisements: Critical Studies of Magazine Advertisements for Market Helps," Writer's Digest, 1927 June (Folder 2: 25)
  - "They Wanted to Abolish the Fourth," Patches, 1927 July 2 (Folder 2: 26)
  - "Market for Opinions," Writer's Digest, 1927 September (Folder 2: 27)
  - Writings on science and philosophy at University of Cincinnati, 1928-1929 (Folder 3: 1-5)
  - "Knowledge by Fiat," The Journal of Philosophy, 1934 July 19 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Book reviews, 1938-1955 (Folder 3: 7-8)
    Includes related correspondence
  - Articles about Russia and the Caucasus published in The Christian Science Monitor, 1942-1943 (Folder 3: 9)
  - "Three Natives Return," Near East Service Quarterly, 1942 October (Folder 3: 10)
  - "Turkey Is Pro-Turkish," Asia and the Americas, 1943 March (Folder 3: 11)
  - "Arrows Across Turkey," The Christian Science Monitor, 1943 March 25 (Folder 3: 12)
  - "How Democratic Is Turkey?" Asia and the Americas, 1945 February (Folder 3: 13)
  - "U.S. Foreign Policy Towards Turkey," Adult Forum at San Francisco Public Library, 1946 November 12 (Folder 4: 1)
  - The People of Turkey, 1946 (Folder 4: 2)
  - "The Dardanelles Drama," The New Leader, 1947 May 3 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Comment on article, "The Kurds as Soviet Pawns" by Mark Alexander in The New Leader, 1947 December 27 (Folder 4: 4)
  - "Turkey Lives on Borrowed Time," Saturday Evening Post, 1948 February 28 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Untitled speech, Presidio of Monterey, 1948 July (Folder 4: 6)
  - "Test of Democracy in Turkey," Middle East Journal, 1950 (Folder 4: 7)
  - "At the Crossroads in the Middle East," Menlo Park Business and Professional Women's Club, 1952 January 22 (Folder 4: 8)
  - "Turkey" and "Turkey Part II," World Affairs Discussion Group Palo Alto, 1952 March 13 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Note cards from speeches, 1952 and undated (Folder 4: 10)
  - "Comments on Turkish affairs subsequent to a visit by Bay Fatin Tozer, editor of Zafer, Ankara,", 1953-1954 (Folder 4: 11)
  - "The People's Choice in Turkey,", 1954 (Folder 4: 12)
  - "Faith and Reason in the West and Islam," The Islamic Journal, 1954 March (Folder 4: 13)
  - Introduction to the translation of Yaban, 1954 April (Folder 4: 14)
  - "Türklerin Ebedî Şefi," Mavi, 1954 December 1, 1954 March (Folder 4: 15)
  - "Resume of Comment and Opinion on Adnan Menderes Prime Minister of Turkey," drafts, 1955 January 25 (Folder 4: 16-17)
  - "About Face in Turkish Government," drafts, Foreign Policy Association Bulletin, 1956 (Folder 4: 18)
- The New Turks: Pioneers of the Republic, 1920-1950 file, 1918, 1935-1956; 4-12 (Box 4-12)
  Consists of correspondence, clippings, drafts of writings, notes, maps, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by form
  - Correspondence with potential publishers, 1947-1949 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Correspondence with publisher (University of Pennsylvania Press), 1948-1951 (Folder 4: 20-23)
  - Correspondence with publisher (University of Pennsylvania Press), 1952-1955 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Drafts, 1948-1951 and undated (Folder 5-7)
    - Draft, undated (Folder 5: 2)
    - Draft with marginal notes by Kerim K. Key and Harry N. Howard, undated (Folder 5: 3-5)
    - Draft, 1948 (Folder 5: 6-9)
    - Draft, 1949 October (Folder 5: 10)
    - Draft, 1949 October (Contd.) (Folder 6: 1-2)
    - Draft, 1950 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Draft, probably 1950 (Folder 6: 4-8)
    - Draft, probably 1950 (Contd.) (Folder 7: 1-2)
    - Page proofs of final manuscript, 1951 (Folder 7: 3-4)
  - Letters of congratulations, 1949-1952 (Folder 8: 1)
  - Permissions to quote, 1949-1950 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Queries and fact checks, undated (Folder 8: 3)
  - Research materials, 1918-1952 and undated (Folder 8-10)
    - Bibliographies on Turkey and the Ottoman Empire, undated (Folder 8: 4)
    - Clippings and sources, 1943-1952 (Folder 8-10)
      Includes used and unused materials
      - General clippings on Turkish politics and government, 1918-1956 and undated (Folder 8)
        - Undated (Folder 8: 5)
        - 1945-1950 (Folder 8: 6-10)
        - 1952-1956 (Folder 8: 11-16)
      - By chapter, 1942-1952 (Folder 8-9)
        - Chapters IV, VI, VIII, 1942-1949 (Folder 8: 17)
        - Chapters IX-XV, 1947-1949 (Folder 8: 18)
        - Chapters XVI-XX, 1948-1950 (Folder 9: 1)
        - Chapters XXI-XXV, 1948-1950 (Folder 9: 2)
        - Chapters XXVI-XXVII, 1945-1949 (Folder 9: 3)
        - Revised edition, 1950-1952 (Folder 9: 4-5)
      - By subject, 1918-1954 (Folder 9-10)
        - Armenia and Armenians, 1945-1948 (Folder 9: 6)
        - Courts and governing bodies, undated (Folder 9: 7)
        - Economy, 1949-1953 (Folder 9: 8)
        - Elections--1950, 1949-1950 (Folder 9: 9)
        - Language and grammar, 1949 and undated (Folder 9: 10-12)
        - Literacy, 1943 (Folder 9: 13)
        - Military, 1947 (Folder 9: 14)
        - NATO, 1951-1953 (Folder 9: 15)
        - Patrick, Mary Mills, 1950 (Folder 10: 1)
        - President and Mrs. Celal Bayar's visit to the Hoover Institution, 1954 (Folder 10: 2-5)
          Includes clippings, booklet, and photographs
        - Presidential speeches, 1939-1947 (Folder 10: 6)
        - Schools, 1949 and undated (Folder 10: 7)
        - Turkish-Soviet relations, 1945-1948 (Folder 10: 8)
        - World War I, 1918 (Folder 10: 9)
        - World War II, 1944-1948 (Folder 10: 10)
    - Maps, 1935-1948 and undated (Folder 10)
      - Turkey, 1937 and undated (Folder 10: 11)
      - World maps and maps of other countries, 1935-1948 (Folder 10: 12-13)
    - Notes on readings and conversations, 1948-1953 and undated (Folder 10: 14-16)
    - Notes on readings and conversations, 1948-1953 and undated (Contd.) (Folder 11: 1-4)
    - Printed materials on Turkish politics, culture, and history, 1944-1955 (Folder 11: 5-10)
  - Reviews, 1951-1952 (Folder 12: 1-4)
  - Royalty statements, 1954 (Folder 12: 5)
- Translations and edited works, 1929, 1943-1956; 12-17 (Box 12-17)
  Typescript and holograph drafts of translations of Turkish writings
  Arranged alphabetically by author or title
  - Article on President İsmet İnönü for Encyclopedia Britannica, 1947 September 15 (Folder 12: 6)
  - Behiç, Hakki, undated (Folder 12: 7)
  - Extracts from a Five Day Speech Delivered by Ghazi Mustafa Kemal, October 1927, 1929 (Folder 12: 8)
    Includes fragments of translations by Eleanor Bisbee
  - Güntekin, Resat Nuri. Yesil Gece (The Green Night), undated. Translated by Adelaide Dwight, 1956 (Folder 12: 9-12)
  - Güntekin, Resat Nuri. Yesil Gece (The Green Night), undated. Translated by Adelaide Dwight, 1956 (Contd.) (Folder 13: 1-2)
  - Halid, Refik (Folder 13)
    - "Yellow Honey," translated by Eleanor Bisbee, 1943 and undated (Folder 13: 3)
    - "The Gray Donkey," translated by Eleanor Bisbee, 1943 August (Folder 13: 4)
  - Hisar, Abdülhak Şinasi. Fahim Bey ve Biz (Fahim Bey and Us), 1942. Translated by Eleanor Bisbee and Methat Esmer, 1950-1952 (Folder 13: 5-9)
  - "History of 19th Century Turkish Literature," translated by Adelaide Dwight, undated (Folder 13: 10)
  - Karaosmanoğlu, Yakup Kadri. Yaban (The Stranger), 1943. Translated by Harold Brodeur with notes by Eleanor Bisbee, 1953-1954 (Folder 14)
    - Correspondence regarding translation and publication, 1953-1954 (Folder 14: 1)
    - Drafts, original and carbon, 1954 April 20 (Folder 14: 2-7)
  - Millî Kalkinma Partisi (National Resurgence Party) charter, 1947 (Folder 14: 8)
  - Seyfettin, Ömer. Short stories translated by Leman Avni Basha and others, 1951-1954 (Folder 14: 9)
  - Turkish election law, 1950 (Folder 14: 10)
  - Yalman, Ahmet Emin (Folder 14-17)
    - Interview with Mustafa Kemal Atatürk, 1922. Translated by Eleanor Bisbee, probably 1950s (Folder 14: 11-12)
    - Turkey in My Time revision, 1951-1955 (Folder 15-17)
      - Correspondence regarding publication of manuscript, 1951-1955 (Folder 15: 1-5)
      - Drafts, 1952 (Folder 15: 6-9)
      - Drafts, 1952 (Contd.) (Folder 16: 1-10)
      - Drafts, 1954 (Folder 17: 1-3)
  - Miscellaneous short stories translated by Eleanor Bisbee, 1942-1943 (Folder 17: 4-5)
  - Miscellaneous translations and related materials, undated (Folder 18: 6-8)
- Speeches and writings by others, 1945-1955; 17-18 (Box 17-18)
  Clippings, course outlines, articles, and speeches.
  Arranged alphabetically by author
  - Biyikoglu, Tevfik, undated (Folder 17: 9)
  - Ekrem, Selma, 1952-1954 (Folder 17: 10-11)
  - Harris, Christina P., 1951-1955 (Folder 17: 12)
  - Hoskins, Halford L., 1955 (Folder 17: 13)
  - Key, Kerim K., 1952-1955 (Folder 17: 14)
  - Key, Kerim K., 1952-1955 (Contd.) (Folder 18: 1-2)
  - Mardin, Virginia Lorraine Woldow, circa 1955 (Folder 18: 3)
  - Yalman, Ahmet Emin, 1945 (Folder 18: 4)
    Newspaper article
- Press Summaries, 1949-1953; 18 (Box 18)
  Consists of translations of press summaries.
  Arranged in two groups chronologically
  - Translations of Turkish newspaper editorials for the U.S. Embassy in Ankara, Turkey, relating to the 1950 elections, 1949-1950 (Folder 18: 5-8)
  - U.S. press comments on Turkey, issued by the Turkish Embassy in Washington, D.C., Office of Press Attaché, 1952-1953 (Folder 18: 9-10)
- Miscellany, 1891, 1914-1953; 18-19 (Box 18-19)
  Letter, pamphlets, clippings, stationery, and shadow puppets.
  - Fragments of correspondence, undated (Folder 18: 11)
  - Letter from Helen [?] to unidentified, 1891 January 30 (Folder 18: 12)
  - Fragment of minutes of the Union Permanente des Délégués du Commerce Étranger, 1914 May 28 (Folder 18: 12)
  - Notes and collected documents from the World Affairs Council and a seminar at the Hoover Library, 1948-1951 (Folder 18: 13)
  - Stanford Turkish Friendship Club stationery, circa 1952 (Folder 18: 14)
  - "Statement by Ambassador Abba Eban Before the Ad Hoc Political Committee," Israel Office of Information, 1952 January 12 (Folder 18: 15)
  - Nichols, Robert L. "Memorial to Alfred Church Lane (1863-1948)," Proceedings Volume of the Geological Society of America Annual Report for 1952, 1953 June (Folder 18: 16)
  - Turkish shadow puppets (Karagöz) and related publications, 1950s (Folder 19)
- Photographs, 1936-1955 and undated; Photo file (Box Photo file)
  Several hundred black and white prints and negatives
  - Outdoor and interior spaces in Turkey, undated (Folder A)
  - Stereographic prints of scenery in the United States, Turkey, Jerusalem, Italy, and France, 1936-1938 (Folder B1-B3)
  - Eleanor Bisbee, family, friends, and former students, 1936-1955 (Folder C1-C2)
  - Social life, politicians, events, and buildings in Turkey, most for publication in The People of Turkey and The New Turks, Pioneers of the Republic, 1920-1950, 1940s (Folder D)
  - 3 photographs of city streets in Turkey, undated (Folder mE)